Curriculum Vitae

iaakashroy.github.io/web

Aakash Roy

Associate Data Scientist III, Elevance Health Inc. Indian Institute of Technology Bombay, India LinkedIn: linkedin.com/in/aakash-roy-18723610b

Gmail: aakashroyiitb@gmail.com GitHub: https://github.com/iaakashRoy

Email: 21i190007@iitb.ac.in

ABOUT ME

I am a Data Scientist with over a year of professional experience, driven by a deep curiosity to unravel the meanings embedded in mathematical equations and natural patterns. I am fascinated by the mysteries of existence and excited about the future. Regarding AI, I am both optimistic and cautious about its potential.

RESEARCH INTERESTS

I am interested in exploring and comparing the boundaries between existing multimodal models and the human brain. I am particularly interested to develop learning algorithms that not only mimic brain-like processing, reasoning, and memory but also serve as tools to uncover brain functions and cognitive mechanisms by combining neuroscience, deep learning, and reinforcement learning for efficient, safe, and aligned models.

EDUCATION

Master of Science (M.Sc.) in Industrial Engineering and Operations Research Jul 2021–Jul 2023 Advisor: Prof. Jayendran Venkateswaran | Indian Institute of Technology, Bombay

CGPA: 8.29/10

Major Courses: Deep Learning for NLP, Distributed Machine Learning, Online Machine Learning, Introduction to Machine Learning, Optimization Models, Engineering Statistics, Stochastic Processes, Linear Systems

Bachelor of Science (B.Sc.) in Mathematics

Jul 2017-Oct 2020

The Bhawanipur Education Society College | University of Calcutta, India

Percentage: 75.5%, 1st Class (Honors)

Major Courses: Abstract Algebra, Linear Algebra, Real Analysis, Differential Equations, Probability, Statistics

West Bengal Council of Higher Secondary Education

Apr 2016–May 2017

Barrackpore Government High School | West Bengal, India

Grade: 90% in Mathematics

West Bengal Board of Secondary Education

Apr 2014–May 2015

Nona Chandanpukur Manmatha Nath Higher Secondary School | West Bengal, India

Grade: 93% in Mathematics

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCES

Associate Data Scientist III | Carelon Global Solutions (Elevance Health Inc.) Jul 2023–Present I am currently involved in Health Insurance Benefit Chatbot Assistant (BeCA) - Orchestration, a multiclass, multilabel in-chat intent detection model development that utilizes Transformers to classify straightforward and ambiguous follow-up questions according to their order in the chat conversation. This work is informed by the paper "On the Use of Transformer-Based Models for Intent Detection Using Clustering Algorithms". The initial deployment of the model was carried out using One-vs-Rest Linear SVM, incorporating a probabilistic approach.

Prior to this, I was part of the development team for the **BeCA - Plan-Level**. Executed various **text chunking**, **model fine-tuning** & **prompt engineering techniques** for faster and accurate information retrieval from plan-level user data and concise answer formation. **This solution is already in production.**

Data Science Intern | Carelon Global Solutions (Elevance Health Inc.)

May-Jul 2022

Conducted an analysis on the Adjustment Inventory of health insurance claims, focusing on classifying which claims require adjustment by performing Exploratory Data Analysis (EDA) on large-scale data to identify trends and patterns for insights. Utilized various NLP & ML techniques, including NER, BoW, TF-IDF, BERT embeddings, PCA, KNN by implementing "A Complete Process of Text Classification System Using State-of-the-Art NLP Models".

Image Caption Generator Using Deep Learning

Jan-May 2023

Instructor: Prof. Pushpak Bhattacharyya, IIT Bombay

Utilized Convolutional neural network (CNN) [VGG19] to process image attributes of Microsoft COCO Dataset. Employed the "Encoder-Decoder" Attention Mechanism from the "Show, attend and Tell: For Image Captioning" paper, combined with Word2Vec embeddings, to establish relationship between text tokens and image pixels by dynamically focusing on relevant parts of an image. Constructed model using Long short-term memory (LSTM), Beam Search for generating the image caption tokens. Achieved BLEU-1 score 72.49(70.7 in paper).

Class-Prior Estimation From Positive Labeled Data

Jan-May 2023

Supervisor: Prof. P Balamurugan, IIT Bombay

Executed the paper "Class-prior estimation for learning from positive and unlabeled data", considering the problem of learning a classifier using only positive and unlabeled samples. Estimated the class-prior on an unlabeled dataset with additional samples coming only from positive class. Utilized penalized L1 divergence for model fitting to cancel the error caused by the absence of negative samples. Experimentally demonstrate the usefulness of penalized f-divergences method on MNIST hand-written digit dataset.

Optimal Algorithms for Non- Smooth Distributed Optimization in Networks

Jan-May 2023

Instructor: Prof. Mayank Baranwal, IIT Bombay

Reviewed and presented the "Distributed optimization of non-smooth convex functions" paper, focusing on Lipschitz continuity and providing optimal convergence rates and algorithms.

Masters Thesis Project: Application of Augmented Reality in Industry

Aug-Dec 2022

Advisor: Prof. Jayendran Venkateswaran, IIT Bombay

Developed an AR application to enhance visualization and problem-solving in industrial processes. Integrated real-time data and 3D model rendering using WebXR, Three.js, and ARCore, compatible with web browsers and mobile devices. Reviewed and demonstrated the potential use cases of AR for improving layout planning, bottleneck identification, and machine maintenance in industrial settings.

Application and Comparison of LinUCB and DivLinUCB in News Recommendation Jan–May 2022

Supervisor: Prof. Manjesh Kumar Hanawal, IIT Bombay

Implemented both the LinUCB, DivLinUCB algorithms with exploration-exploitation trade-off and the paper "Diversity in News recommendation using contextual bandits" to find out whether it is effective in building recommendation engines. Instead focusing solely on maximizing click through rate, which may overexpose some articles whereas the remaining ones may be recommended very rarely, we considered the "historical frequency", or the number of times it has been recommended as the "cost" of recommending it. This project is a comparison of performance between the above mentioned algorithms. Achieved CTR value of 0.9508 with alpha value 0.001. Validated the accuracy and correctness by observing the UCB values of predicted arms.

Industry Project: AI Driven Credit Scoring Model For Farmers (Virenxia, TCAAI) Jan-May 2022

Supervisor: Prof. Usha Anantakumar, IIT Bombay

Developed a credit scoring model for farmers, addressing challenges such as low financial inclusion, limited access to credit, and unstructured data. Machine learning techniques, including K-Means and Hierarchical Clustering, were used to group farmers based on behavior, with key factors being crop production, land area, and selling price.

Optimization Modeling and Data Visualization

Jul 2021-Apr 2022

Instructor: Prof. P Balamurugan, IIT Bombay

Explored various Optimization models using **pyomo**, solved them using **cbc**, **glpk**. Implemented **Gradient descent**, **Line search**, **Newton's algorithm and BFGS algorithm** for solving Unconstrained Nonlinear optimization problems & performed loss minimization. Visualized data using **seaborn**, **matplotlib** and summarized using **descriptive statistics**. Performed **Column normalization**, **Clustering by k-means**, **Dimensionality reduction by PCA**.

ACHIEVEMENTS

ACHIEVEMENTS		
Recipient of the Departmental Te Indian Institute of Technology, Bomba	-	2021–2023
Received Pre-Placement Offer after completion of AI/ML Internship Carelon Global Solutions (Elevance Health Inc.)		2022
- -	in India for MSc Programme in the only ons Research department in India y	2021
Cleared Chennai Mathematical Institute Master's Entrance Examination Organized by the Chennai Mathematical Institute, Chennai, India		2021
Selected for the Mathematics Training and Talent Search program Organized by the Mathematics Training and Talent Search Trust, India		2019
Bagged Certificate in Mathematics Talent and Quiz Competition Analytica Organized by the Department of Mathematics, St. Xavier's College, Kolkata, India		2019
Recipient of Swami Vivekananda Merit Cum Means Undergraduate Scholarship Offered by the Government of West Bengal		2018-2020
COURSES		
Comprehensive list of pertinent courses completed during my BSc and MSc studi $B.Sc\text{-}M.Sc$ Coursework		es 2017-2023
Compilation of various other coun Other Relevant Courses	rses studied from different online platforms	2022-2024
WORKSHOPS AND SEMINARS		
Data Science Bootcamp organized IIT Bombay and DPhi	d by Analytics club	Jun 2022
Python & Introduction to Machin University of Calcutta	ne Learning	Feb 2019
National Seminar and Conference on Contemporary Research in Theoretical and Applicable Mathematics $University\ of\ Calcutta$		Aug 2018
Hands-on workshop on programming languages for Mathematicians $University\ of\ Calcutta$		Feb 2018
CERTIFICATIONS		
DS0101EN: Introduction to Data Science, IBM		Dec-Jan 2021
Machine Learning A-Z: Hands-On Python & R In Data Science, Udemy		Jul-Dec 2021
SKILLS		
Machine Learning General Software Engineering Data Visualization Misc Languages	TensorFlow, PyTorch Python (Numpy, Pandas, Scikit-learn, Scipy), PySpark Matplotlib, Seaborn Git, Docker, Visual Studio, Jupyter, PostMan, AWS, Langlish, Bengali, Hindi	T _E X, Pyomo